<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='no'?>
<doxygen xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="compound.xsd" version="1.8.6">
  <compounddef id="kinematicspage" kind="page">
    <compoundname>kinematicspage</compoundname>
    <title>The kinematics module</title>
    <detaileddescription>
<para>The <ref refid="index_1kinematics" kindref="member">The kinematics and Planning module</ref> module provides interfaces and their implementations for path planning and kinematics (forward, inverse). It is possible to easily instantiate different versions of path planners and use the optimal planner for the desired purpose. Currently, there are 3 different planners implemented:<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><ref refid="classkukadu_1_1SimplePlanner" kindref="compound">kukadu::SimplePlanner</ref>: This planner implements a simple interpolation in joint space in order to compute a plan from one joint position to another. In order to do so, it uses the <ulink url="http://www.reflexxes.ws/">Reflexxes</ulink> library. For Cartesian planning it simple performs inverse kinematics for the target position and interpolates in joint space. It does not support any functionality for obstacle avoidance or for fulfilling specific constraints.</para></listitem><listitem><para>kukadu::KomoPlanner:</para></listitem><listitem><para>kukadu::MoveItKinematics:</para></listitem></itemizedlist>
</para><para><heading level="1">kukadu::KomoPlanner</heading>
</para><para>The next code snippet shows, how kukadu can be used in combination with KOMO. KOMO is a robust and stable path planner and we recommend to use this planner. If you don&apos;t select a specific planner, KOMO will be used automatically.</para><para><programlisting></programlisting></para><para><heading level="2">Prerequisites</heading>
</para><para>The only prerequisite is the started kukie controller. Further, the environment variable <emphasis>KUKADU_HOME</emphasis> needs to be set to the base folder of kukadu. This variable should be set in your bash by <programlisting><codeline><highlight class="normal">export<sp/>KUKADU_HOME=%INSERT_YOUR_PATH_TO_YOUR_CATKIN%/src/kukadu</highlight></codeline>
</programlisting> Alternatively, instead of exporting this value every time, you can also add this line to your <emphasis>.bashrc</emphasis> file.</para><para><heading level="2">Description</heading>
</para><para>In this example, most lines should look familiar to you. If not, please check out again chapter <ref refid="robotpage" kindref="compound">The robot module</ref>. The new part is found in lines 15 - 17. In line 15 a new KOMO instance is created. In lines 16 and 17 this instance is set as the planner and kinematics solver in your <ref refid="classkukadu_1_1KukieControlQueue" kindref="compound">kukadu::KukieControlQueue</ref>. In the current version of kukadu, this theoretically is not required, as KOMO is the standard planner. However, you can set it explitely, which is done in the shown example. Whenever the functions <ref refid="classkukadu_1_1ControlQueue_1ad11059100321b24a1af8ef7de8314353" kindref="member">kukadu::ControlQueue::jointPtp()</ref> and <ref refid="classkukadu_1_1ControlQueue_1a1bfa23a8ce6319f6ef0ed9208e896054" kindref="member">kukadu::ControlQueue::cartesianPtp()</ref> are used, the planner that was set in lines 16 and 17 is consulted. The generated plan is executed immediately.</para><para>It is also possible to use the planner directly without calling the PtP methods of <ref refid="classkukadu_1_1ControlQueue" kindref="compound">kukadu::ControlQueue</ref>. You find these functions in the API description of <ref refid="classkukadu_1_1PathPlanner" kindref="compound">kukadu::PathPlanner</ref>. You can execute the generated plan by using <ref refid="classkukadu_1_1ControlQueue_1a0025c5c010a1b33d637e52fb24f767b2" kindref="member">kukadu::ControlQueue::setNextTrajectory()</ref>. An example on how this is done is given in the next code snippet.</para><para><programlisting></programlisting></para><para><heading level="1">kukadu::MoveItKinematics</heading>
</para><para>MoveIt is one of the standard ways in the ROS universe for robot control and path planning. kukadu also provides an interface to this framework.</para><para><programlisting></programlisting></para><para><heading level="2">Prerequisites</heading>
</para><para>In order to use kukadu with MoveIt, you need to upload the robot model and the MoveIt configuration to the parameter server. Typically, this can be done by using the launch files generated by the MoveIt configuration setup. You might execute something similar to <programlisting><codeline><highlight class="normal">roslaunch<sp/>uibk_robot_moveit_config<sp/>demo.launch</highlight></codeline>
</programlisting> If you are not familiar with MoveIt, please consult the <ulink url="http://moveit.ros.org/documentation/tutorials/">MoveIt tutorial</ulink> on how to set up MoveIt for your robot.</para><para><heading level="2">Description</heading>
</para><para>The code is very similar to the one that was described for the KOMO planner. As both planners (MoveIt and KOMO) implement the same kukadu interface (<ref refid="classkukadu_1_1PathPlanner" kindref="compound">kukadu::PathPlanner</ref>), the only difference is found in line 15, where you create a kukadu::MoveItKinematics instance instead of an kukadu::KomoPlanner instance. The rest of the code is independent of the concrete planner.</para><para><heading level="1"><ref refid="classkukadu_1_1SimplePlanner" kindref="compound">kukadu::SimplePlanner</ref></heading>
</para><para>TODO: this code is not tested yet</para><para><programlisting></programlisting></para><para><heading level="2">Prerequisites</heading>
</para><para>None</para><para>Prev (<ref refid="robotpage" kindref="compound">The robot module</ref>), Next (<ref refid="controlpage" kindref="compound">The control module</ref>) </para>    </detaileddescription>
  </compounddef>
</doxygen>
